(
"ai_sub_version": "1.9.2",
"subtitles_prompt_version": 2,
"complete": true,
"max_retries_exceeded": false,
"settings": (
"ai": (
"model": "gemini-cli:gemini-3-flash-preview",
"rpm": 4,
"tpm": 250000,
"google": (
"file_cache_ttl": 10,
"use_files_api": true
),
"gemini_cli": (
"timeout": 600
)
),
"split": (
"max_seconds": 300,
"re_encode": (
"enabled": true,
"fps": 1,
"height": 360,
"bitrate_kb": 35,
"encoder": "libx264"
)
),
"thread": (
"uploads": 4,
"re_encode": 2,
"subtitles": 8
),
"retry": (
"run": 3,
"max": 9,
"delay": 30
),
"log": (
"level": "info",
"timestamps": false,
"scrub": true
)
行くよ、開拓者。
Let's go, Pioneers.
ちいさな心が決めたこと
作詞・作曲：AZKi 編曲：SCRAMBLES
What the Little Heart Decided
Lyrics/Composition: AZKi Arrangement: SCRAMBLES
あの日選んで決めた道は
The path I chose and decided on that day...
間違いだったんだろって過去を恨んでみても
...even if I resent the past, thinking it was a mistake.
土砂降りの雨が責め立てて
The pouring rain keeps blaming me,
俯いた顔は酷く弱いことに気づいた
and I realized my downcast face was terribly weak.
この先には叶えたいことや
Since there are things I want to fulfill ahead,
夢があるから
and dreams too...
目を逸らさないように
I won't look away.
正解はない 誰だって一人で
There's no right answer; anyone, alone,
思うまま始まっていくこの物語
starts this story as they wish.
今はただ走って
Now, just keep running,
季節を駆け巡って
racing through the seasons,
見えない暗闇の中で
inside the unseen darkness.
痛みだってあるよ
There will be pain too.
戸惑いだってあるよ
There will be confusion too.
それでもここで生きていくと
Even so, to live here is what...
決めたんだ
...I have decided.
決めたから
Because I've decided,
前を向いて
I'll face forward.
生き方を誰かに決められて
Having my way of life decided by someone else,
本当はそうじゃなかったと今更嘆いたって
it's too late to lament that it wasn't meant to be.
味方も希望もあらわれなくて
With no allies or hope appearing,
喧騒の中でどこか彷徨い果てていた
I was wandering lost within the hustle and bustle.
この先には奏でたい音や
Since there are sounds I want to play ahead,
歌があるから
and songs too...
耳を澄ますように
I'll listen closely.
間違いはない 誰だって一人で
There are no mistakes; anyone, alone,
綴り続けられていくこの物語
continues to write this story.
過去 今 未来が
The past, present, and future
あなたを駆け巡って
will race through you,
理想と現実の中で
between ideals and reality.
泣きたくもなるよ
I'll feel like crying sometimes.
諦めたくなるよ
I'll feel like giving up sometimes.
それでもここで生きていくと
Even so, to live here is what...
決めたんだ
...I have decided.
決めたから
Because I've decided.
走り出すよ
I'll start running
生まれ変わっても この話をしよう
Even if I'm reborn, let's talk about this
この人生で良かったと
That I'm glad to have this life
痛みは力に
Pain becomes strength
戸惑いは期待に
Confusion becomes expectation
そうしてここで生きていくんだと
And so, I'll live here
今はただ走って
Now I'm just running
季節を駆けて巡って
Through the seasons, round and round
見えない暗闇の中で
In the invisible darkness
痛みだってあるよ
There is pain
戸惑いだってあるよ
There is confusion
それでもここで生きていくと
Even so, I will live here
決めたんだ
I've decided
決めたから
Because I've decided
前を向いて
Look forward
こんあずきー！
Kon-AZKi!
右手にマイク、左手に地図
Mic in the right hand, map in the left hand
あなたのハートをゼロゲッサー！
Zero-guess your heart!
ということで、AZKiです！
And so, I'm AZKi!
今日は、AZKi 5th Birthday Live
Today is AZKi's 5th Birthday Live
DESTiNATiON -ちいさな心が行く先-
DESTiNATiON -Where the small heart goes-
お越しいただきありがとうございます！
Thank you for coming!
早いもので、5回目の誕生日を迎えます。
Time flies, I'm celebrating my 5th birthday.
今日お祝いに来てくれてみんな、ありがとう！
Thank you everyone for coming to celebrate today!
ありがとうございます。
Thank you.
今日のですね、ハッシュタグは #AZKi生誕ライブ2023 でございます。
Today's hashtag is #AZKiBirthdayLive2023.
たくさんスクショ & ツイート よろしくお願いいたします。
Please take lots of screenshots and tweet them.
さて、今回のライブタイトル
Well, this live's title
DESTiNATiON -ちいさな心が行く先- なんですけど
DESTiNATiON -Where the small heart goes-
AZKiが命名いたしました。
AZKi named it.
このタイトルに込めた意味を
The meaning behind this title
今日のこのライブを通して、みんなに伝えることができたらいいなと思っています。
I hope I can convey the meaning through this live today.
DESTiNATiON、つまり目的地とは
DESTiNATiON, in other words, where the destination is
どこなのか
Is it?
AZKiはどこへ向かっていくのか
Where is AZKi heading?
目的地をゲスできるのか
Can you 'guess' the destination?
ということで、最後まで目を離さないでくださいね。
So, don't take your eyes off until the end.
ということで、1曲目は『ちいさな心が決めたこと』ということで
So, the first song was "What a small heart decided"
私が初めて作詞作曲させていただいた曲です。
It's the first song I wrote and composed.
今日のこのサブタイトルにも繋がっています。
It also connects to today's subtitle.
活動始めた時の気持ちだったり
The feelings when I started my activities
こうして音楽を届けたいという気持ちを忘れないように
So as not to forget the feeling of wanting to deliver music
今日1曲目に改めて歌わせていただきました。
I sang it again today as the first song.
そして、本日は最後には何やら重大発表
And, at the end of today, there's some kind of major announcement
事前に告知しておりますけれども、メンバー限定でアンコールライブもございますので
There will also be an encore live for members only as announced
ぜひぜひ、こちらもお見逃しなく！
So please, don't miss that either!
ということで今日は本当に盛りだくさんなので
So today is really packed
どんどん歌っていきたいと思います！
I want to keep on singing!
それでは、次の曲に行きたいと思います。
Now, let's move on to the next song.
聴いてください、without U。
Please listen, without U.
君がいるから
Because you are here
一人じゃないから
Because I'm not alone
盛り上がっていきましょう！
Let's get excited!
ずっと一人だけで
Always by myself
同じことばかり
Just the same things
なんか寂しくなっちゃうよね
It kind of makes me feel lonely
...明日もわからない
...don't even know what tomorrow brings,
こんな足りないものみたいに
just like something so incomplete.
初めからおしまいまで　きっと小さな私
From the beginning to the end, my small self
世界に怯えている
is surely afraid of the world.
だから without U　君がいない時きっと
So, without U, when you're not here,
私は私でいられないんだ
I surely can't be myself.
I need U　私を　見ていて聞いて
I need U, watch me, listen to me,
そしたらきっと届けられるから
because then I'll surely be able to reach you.
君がいるって
Because you are here,
一人じゃないって
because I'm not alone.
歩き出したのは　私だけじゃなくて
It wasn't just me who started walking,
きっとこうしている時でも
surely even at times like this.
君はずっとずっと　頑張っていたんだね
You've been doing your best all along,
私は全部見てるから
because I've been watching everything.
爪先から天辺まで　小さな心全部伝える
From my toes to the top of my head, I'll convey all of my small heart,
想いがここに
the feelings are right here.
それは without U　君のそばにいるよ
That's why without U, I'm by your side,
どんなに辛く想った時でも
no matter how painful it feels.
I with U　聞かせて　君の声
I with U, let me hear your voice,
そこに私の声を重ねたら
if I layer my voice over yours,
そばにいる
I'm right by your side.
もらったものを抱えて
Holding on to what I've received,
少し足りないくらいだよ
it's almost not enough.
一人じゃない　わかってるね
You're not alone, you know that, right?
いつまでこうしていられるの
How long can we stay like this?
そんなことわからないよ
I don't know such things,
わからないから歌うんだよ
that's why I sing.
君といるこの瞬間
To make this moment with you
大切なものにするために
something truly precious.
そうだ without U　君がいない時きっと
That's right, without U, when you weren't here,
私は私でいられなかったんだ
I surely couldn't have been myself.
I need U　私を　見ていて聞いて
I need U, watch me, listen to me,
そしたらきっときっとこれからも
then surely, surely from now on too.
だから with U　君の中にいるよ
So, with U, I'm inside you,
君がくれたものその代わりに
in exchange for what you gave me.
I with U　どうか覚えていて
I with U, please remember,
私がここに立つ時はいつも
whenever I stand here...
君といるから
I'm with you,
一人じゃないから
because I'm not alone.
in this world
愛が言葉を見失ってる
Love has lost its words,
空が涙を降らせていたんだ
the sky was making tears fall.
誰のために
For whom,
何のために
for what,
これが運命だというの
do you call this fate?
嘘が街を包み込んでいる
Lies are enveloping the town,
鳥が飛べずに声を上げていた
a bird couldn't fly and was raising its voice.
たったひとつの存在を灯す
Lighting up but a single existence,
この場所で君を待ってる
I'm waiting for you here.
世界はとても苦しそうでした
The world seemed to be in so much pain,
私に何ができるというの
what could I possibly do?
歌うことが正しいかなんて
Whether singing is the right thing to do...
今も答えは見つからないけど
...I still haven't found the answer yet.
確かなのは君がいたから
What is certain is that because you were there...
私はここにいるの
...I am here now.
何回何十回だって
No matter how many tens of times,
君と出会うから
I'll meet you again.
夜が明けてゆく 光が降り注ぎ
The night is dawning, light is pouring down.
喜び悲しみを携え前を向く
Carrying joy and sorrow, I look forward.
君と生きてく ここでこの場所で
I'll live with you here, in this place.
それが私の世界だ
That is my world.
その一秒一瞬が煌めく
Every second, every moment shines.
過去が虹を壊したとしても
Even if the past destroyed the rainbow,
夢が街を暗く落とそうとしても
even if dreams try to darken the town,
大丈夫だから そばにいるよ
it's okay, because I'm by your side.
君に笑ってほしいんだ
I want you to smile.
生まれた意味を探しているの
I'm looking for the meaning of my birth.
転んでもただ走り続けていく
Even if I fall, I'll just keep running.
今を知って 明日を願った
Knowing the present, I wished for tomorrow.
心が叫びたがってる
My heart wants to scream.
タイムマシンに乗ってさ 別の未来を選べたのなら
If I could take a time machine and choose a different future,
君のいない世界を想像する？
would I imagine a world without you?
そんな世界は想像できない
I can't imagine such a world.
君に届きますように この声が この歌が
I hope this voice, this song reaches you.
何回何十回だって 君を選ぶから
No matter how many tens of times, I'll choose you.
夜が滲んでゆく 地平の彼方へ
The night is blurring towards the horizon.
響く呼吸の音 確かに感じた
I certainly felt the sound of echoing breath.
始めよう 君との未来を
Let's begin the future with you.
繋いだ手を離さないで
Don't let go of my held hand.
大きな声で名前を呼んで
Call my name in a loud voice.
奇跡を駆け抜けて
Run through miracles.
どこまでも行けるよ
We can go anywhere.
ここからもう一度 君と私で始めよう
Let's start over from here, you and I.
無限の中に生まれる物語を
A story born in infinity,
君と歩いていく
I'll walk it with you.
この世界が悲しみに溢れたとしても
Even if this world is filled with sadness,
私は歌を歌い続けていく
I'll keep on singing songs.
君と生きてく ここでこの場所で
I'll live with you here, in this place.
それが私の世界だ
That is my world.
その一秒一瞬が煌めく
Every second, every moment shines.
傷つき涙を流す君が 幸せだと思える世界になりますように
I hope the world becomes a place where even when you're hurt and crying, you can feel happy.
願いを込め歌う
I sing with this wish.
画面の中の君が好き
I Like the You Inside the Screen
君を初めて見つけた時
When I first found you,
なぜか心 揺さぶられたんだ
for some reason, my heart was shaken.
作り物に命を宿す 君の輝きは本物だった
Breathing life into a fabrication, your brilliance was real.
楽しそうな君は素敵だった
You looked so happy, it was wonderful.
画面の中の君が好き
I like the you inside the screen.
ただ君が変われたらいい
I just wish you could change.
本当の君と実は違うとしても
Even if you're actually different from the real you.
新しい扉を開けて 息をしようよ
Open a new door and let's take a breath.
嘘も本当も関係ないから
Because lies and truth don't matter.
息をしている瞬間を僕ら
The moments we are breathing, we...
届けたいんだ
I want to reach you
君が好きだから
Because I love you
もしも君が生きづらいなら
If life is hard for you
好きな顔と服を着てもいい
It's okay to wear the face and clothes you like
もしも君がやめたくなっても
If you ever want to quit
僕らは止めたりしないからさ
We won't try to stop you
生きやすい場所を探せばいい
Just look for a place where you can breathe easy
君の言葉が僕に刺さった
Your words pierced through me
君の歌に僕は揺さぶられた
Your song shook my soul
君の配信に、僕は夢中になった。
I got hooked on your streams.
画面の中の君が、僕を救ってくれた。
The you inside the screen saved me.
いつか画面の外もなくなっては
If one day even the world outside the screen disappears
画面の中にいた君のことを
About you, who was inside the screen
君自身が好きでいてくれてたら
If you could love yourself
嬉しいな
I'd be so happy
ただ君が笑えたらいい
I just want you to be able to smile
本当の君と
Even if the real you
実は違うとしたって
is actually different
新しい扉を開けた
A new door has opened
君の奇跡は
The miracle that is you
嘘も本当も抱きしめるよ
I'll embrace both the lies and the truth
君にとってこの場所が生きる糧になれたなら
If this place could become your source of life
僕は幸せだ
I would be happy
幸せだから
Because I'm happy
みんなも一緒に歌ってね！
Everyone, sing along too!
ありがとう！
Thank you!
ということで、お聴きいただいたのは
And with that, the songs you just heard were
Without U、In This World、
Without U, In This World,
画面の中の君が好きでした！
and "I Love You Inside the Screen"!
いかがでしたでしょうか？
How did you like them?
これまでね、AZKiにとって欠かせない楽曲を選んで
I chose songs that have been essential to AZKi until now
歌わせていただきました。
to perform for you today.
そう、最近AZKiを知ってくれたという方もきっと多いと思います。
Yes, I'm sure there are many of you who have only recently gotten to know AZKi.
初めてライブ見るよっていう人ー？
Is there anyone watching a live for the first time?
お、お、いますね。いますね。いますね。
Oh, oh, there are some. There are! There are!
いやー、嬉しい。こうやってね、ライブをみんなで見に来てくれる日が
Wow, I'm so happy. A day where everyone comes to watch the live like this...
本当に、本当に本当に嬉しいです。
It truly, truly, truly makes me happy.
えー、AZKi今年、本当に大きな転機があった年だなと思ってまして、
AZKi feels that this year has truly been a year of big turning points,
地図のお姉さんと言われるようになったきっかけの年でもあったし、
It was the year I started being called the "Map Lady",
今までのね、こうずっと歌を中心に活動してきたんですけれども、
Up until now, I've mostly focused my activities on singing,
ま、その歌とは違う側面からみんなにも知ってもらえたり、
but having everyone get to know me through a different side from singing,
楽しんでもらえたりする機会があったのは、すごくとても大きかったで す。
and having opportunities for you to enjoy that was a very, very big deal.
なんで、ちょっと改めてね、なんかこう、AZKiってどんな、どんな活動をしてきたの？みたいなところの
So, I'd like to talk a bit more about what kind of activities AZKi has done up until now,
話になるんですけど、えーっと本当に、うーんとこれまで決してこう平坦な道ではありませんでした。
but it's really... well, it certainly wasn't a smooth road up to this point.
今ではですね、ホロライブ所属で活動させてもらっていますが、
Currently, I'm active as a member of Hololive,
活動始めたときはですね、INNK Musicという音楽レーベルで活動を始めました。
but when I first started, I was with a music label called INNK Music.
そして、AZKiは実は、2022年の7月に活動終了予定だったんですけど、
And actually, AZKi was scheduled to end activities in July 2022,
その活動終了予定であったルートαから、その、そこ終わらないで終わりの向こうを目指す
but from that "Route Alpha" where I was supposed to end, instead of ending there, aiming for what's beyond the end...
ルートβというね、えーっと道の分岐があったんですよ。そうなんです。
there was a fork in the road called "Route Beta". That's right.
はい、そして、ま、自分の中でも、すごく大きかったのが、
Yes, and what was also very big for me personally,
INNK Musicの解散ということで、
was the dissolution of INNK Music,
あのタイミングで...
At that time...
...えっと、卒業も考えていました。
...well, I was actually thinking about graduating.
でも今こうやって、えー、ライブができて、AZKiがこうやって存在しているのは...
But the reason I'm able to hold a live like this and that AZKi exists here now...
...ま、そのAZKiを続けようと決めた私自身でもあり...
...is because of myself, who decided to continue as AZKi...
...ま、その思いをね、受け入れてくれたホロライブやカバーの皆さん...
...and because of Hololive, Cover, and everyone who accepted those feelings...
...がいて、ま、その本当にそういうことを決めようと思った大きな...
...and the biggest factor that made me decide to keep going...
...大きなその背中を押してくれたっていうのは本当に開拓者の皆がいたからです。
...the ones who gave me that big push forward, were really all of the Pioneers.
一番こう辛い時に頑張っていた過去の私にも感謝したいし...
I want to thank my past self who worked hard during the toughest times...
...昔からね、応援してくれている開拓者の皆にも感謝したいです。
...and I also want to thank all the Pioneers who have supported me for so long.
そして、今今日こうやって応援してくれる皆がいるから、今日この今のAZKiがあります。
And because all of you are here supporting me today, the AZKi of right now exists.
本当にありがとう。
Thank you so much.
2023年、え、今日からね、そう、ちょうど折り返し地点ですね。
It's 2023, and from today... yes, it's exactly the halfway point.
ま、またこれからどんなことが起こるのか、どんなことができるのか、ぜひ楽しみにしていてほしいです。
I want you to look forward to what will happen and what I'll be able to achieve from here on out.
はい。ね。それでは、ちょっとしんみりとしたところで、次の曲に行きたいなと思います。
Alright. Well then, on that sentimental note, I'd like to move on to the next song.
AZKiの本当にこの、ま、今日は『目的地』っていうタイトルになってるんですけど...
AZKi's... well, today's title is "DESTiNATiON"...
ま、そういう目的地に行く時にはいろんな分岐点があって、そのAZKiの分岐点には本当にたくさんの人がいて、大切な人がたくさんいます。
But on the way to a destination, there are many turning points, and at my turning points, there were many precious people.
そんなね、大切な人に届けたい歌を、えー、歌いたいと思います。
I'd like to sing a song that I want to deliver to those precious people.
それでは聴いてください。『大切なお知らせ』。
Please listen. "Important Announcement".
大切なお知らせ
作詞・作曲・編曲：渡名喜 航
Important Announcement
Lyrics, Composition, Arrangement: Wataru Tonaki
今まで私と一緒にいてくれて本当にありがとう
Thank you so much for being with me all this time
もうすぐお別れだね
It's almost time to say goodbye
二人で刻んだ皺をなぞって
Tracing the wrinkles we carved together
ずっといつものくだらない話をしようよ
Let's keep having our usual silly conversations forever
今まで本当に色々あったね
A lot has really happened up until now
始発で旅したり 誕生日忘れたり
Traveling on the first train, forgetting birthdays
ディナーの値段見て ヒヤヒヤしたり
Getting nervous looking at dinner prices
全部全部が宝物だから
Because every single bit is a treasure
全部全部が
Because every single bit...
全部が
Everything is
あなたと繋がってるから
...connects me to you
connected to you
夢で会えたらまた話そうね
If we meet in a dream, let's talk again
酸いも甘いもあなたから教わった
I learned both the bitter and the sweet from you
心の微熱は冷めることなく
The slight fever in my heart never cools down
ずっとずっと灯し続けて
Continuing to burn forever and ever
恋し続けて
Continuing to love
今あなたのこと愛してる
Now, I love you
今まで私と一緒にいてくれて本当にありがとう
Thank you so much for being with me all this time
いつも言ってるけど
I'm always saying it, but...
知らない世界を教えてくれた
You taught me about worlds I didn't know
全部全部が新しい景色で
Everything, everything was a new sight
全部にあなたが残っているよ
You remain in everything
全部に
In everything
あなたが残っているよ
you remain
いつか必ず会いに行くから
I will definitely go to meet you someday
あなたと過ごして後悔はなかったよ
I have no regrets about spending time with you
心の微熱は冷めることなく
The slight fever in my heart never cools down
ずっとずっと灯し続けて
Continuing to burn forever and ever
恋し続けて
Continuing to love
今あなたのこと愛してる
Now, I love you
春色模様の空見上げて
Looking up at the spring-colored sky
過ぎ行く時間に身を委ねた
Surrendering myself to the passing time
思い出は尽きることなく
Memories are endless
あぁ　もう少しだけ
Ah, just a little more
もう少しだけ
Just a little more
触れさせて
Let me touch you
桜が零れ散る
The cherry blossoms are spilling and falling
いのち
Life
作詞・作曲・編曲：瀬名航
Lyrics, Composition, Arrangement: Sena Wataru
息をしている
I'm breathing
君は生きている
You are living
当然のことを誰も疑わないの
No one doubts what is obvious
息をしている
I'm breathing
表に見えている
Visible on the surface
生の裏側　私にとっての何か
The other side of life, something to me
鼓動がドクドクしている
My heart is thumping
叩かれても腐らずに
Without rotting even if I'm beaten
此処で歌うよ
I'll sing here
ボタン一つのいのち
A life of a single button
最後まで私のこと覚えててくれるの？
Will you remember me until the end?
消えてしまいそうなの　わかってよ
I feel like I'm going to disappear, please understand
わかってよ　ねえ
Please understand, hey
本当はどこなの　恋と生は違うでしょ
Where is it really? Love and life are different, right?
君が忘れちゃったら　私は居なくなるの
If you forget me, I will be gone
いのちのような　夢を見てるよ
I'm having a dream like life
またねバイバイ
See you again, bye-bye
息をしている
I'm breathing
だから生きている
That's why I'm living
自己証明を欲しがって　欲しがっているんだ
I'm wanting, wanting self-validation
音が止まって
The sound stops
動かなくなって
Stops moving
そんな私を君は笑ってくれるかな
Will you laugh at me like that?
鼓動がドクドクしている
My heart is thumping
嫌われても腐らずに
Without rotting even if I'm hated
此処で歌うよ
I'll sing here
気分次第のいのち
A life of mood
最後まで私のこと見届けくれるの？
Will you watch over me until the end?
覚めてしまいそうなの　わかってよ
I feel like I'm going to wake up, please understand
わかってよ　ねえ
Please understand, hey
声が聞こえるんだよ　塩辛い涙が出ちゃうほど
I can hear your voice, so much that salty tears come out
君が忘れちゃったら　私は居なくなるの
If you forget me, I will be gone
いのちのような　夢を見てるよ
I'm having a dream like life
またねバイバイ
See you again, bye-bye
ふさぎこんだあの日を
That day when I was depressed
軽く弄らないで　やめて
Don't toy with it lightly, stop
それが生きる糧になるから
Because that will become the food for living
大丈夫　ずっと私は
It's okay, I'll always
歌い続けるから
Keep on singing
最後まで私は
Until the end, I...
生きているか分からないけど
...don't know if I'm even alive, but...
君がくれた言葉は
...the words you gave me...
確かに残ってる
...certainly remain.
最後まで私の
Will you remember...
こと覚えててくれるの？
...me until the very end?
いつ死んでしまうだろ
I wonder when I'll die.
わかんない　わかんないよって
I don't know, I just don't know.
痛いくらい気持ちが
My feelings synchronize...
シンクロする時もあるけれど
...to the point of pain sometimes, but...
君が忘れちゃったら
If you forget me...
私は居なくなるの
...I will disappear.
命のような
I'm having a dream...
夢を見てるよ
...like life itself.
またねバイバイ
See you again, bye-bye.
瀬名 航
Wataru Sena
いのち/AZKi
Inochi / AZKi
サプライズゲスト、そらちゃんに来てもらいました！
A surprise guest, Sora-chan is here with us!
こんそめー！そらとものそらです！AZKiちゃんお誕生日おめでとう！
Kon-some! It's Tokino Sora from Soratomo! Happy birthday, AZKi-chan!
ありがとー！
Thank you!
ここからはSorAZでお届けしまーす！
From here, we'll perform as SorAZ!
いぇーい！
Yay!
ただ独り言綴った
I just wrote down a monologue.
ただ始まりたくて走った
I just wanted to start, so I ran.
遠く暗がりに灯った
Lit up in the distance in the dark...
それは眩しすぎた名前
...that was a name too dazzling.
それは優しすぎる思い出
That's a memory too kind.
もっと近づけと手を伸ばした
I reached out my hand to get closer.
思いがけず結び合った
Unexpectedly, we became connected.
ほら今バイカラー
Look, now we're bicolor...
僕らになった
...we've become one.
Parade, Parade, Parade 輝くんだよ
Parade, Parade, Parade, it's shining.
悔しさも愛おしさも
Both frustration and preciousness...
連れておいで
...bring them along.
風、夢、羽、飛び立ってさ
Wind, dreams, wings, take flight.
ささやかな祈りの光
A small light of prayer...
終わりなき兆し
...a never-ending sign.
君を見つけたこと
Finding you...
胸を張れるよ
...is something I can be proud of.
ここから　これから
From here, from now on...
Our Bright Parade, Parade
まだ頼りない予感も
Even the still-unreliable premonitions...
歌を恥ずかしくなんてないよ
...singing is nothing to be ashamed of.
誰も解けないイマジナリー
An imaginary that no one can solve.
いつかまた逢えるまじない
A charm to meet again someday.
あの日ゼロに始まったストーリー
The story that started from zero that day.
数え切れない言の葉
Countless words...
飾るような思いじゃないさ
...it's not a feeling for show.
ほら今僕らを一つと呼ぼう
Look, now let's call us 'one'.
Parade, Parade, Parade 美しいんだよ
Parade, Parade, Parade, it's beautiful.
許しあえる切な夜はきらめく
The painful nights of mutual forgiveness sparkle.
雨、晴れ、糧、纏いなさい
Rain, sun, nourishment, wrap yourself in them.
相応しい旅路とは
A journey that's fitting is...
君と歩くことさ
...walking with you.
君と歩くことなんだ
It's walking with you.
「ただいま」を聞けば
If I hear 'I'm home'...
「おかえり」って叫ぶよ
...I'll shout 'Welcome back!'
当たり前じゃないか
Isn't that natural?
...輝くんだよ
...shining bright.
暗がりを満たすのは
What fills the darkness is
君だ 僕だ
you and me.
パレパレパレ 輝くんだよ
Parade, parade, parade, shining bright.
悔しさも愛おしさも 全ておいで
Regret and affection, let it all come.
風 夢 羽 飛び立てるさ
Wind, dreams, wings, we can fly.
ささやかな祈りは光 終わりなき誓い
A modest prayer is light, an endless vow.
君と飛び込んでゆく 素敵なスタートさ
Diving in with you, a wonderful start.
ここから これから
From here, from now on,
Our Bright Parade, Parade!
なんと！サプライズゲストにそらちゃんが来てくれましたー！
Guess what! Sora-chan has come as a surprise guest!
はーい！あずちゃんおめでとー！
Hello! Congratulations, Azu-chan!
ありがとー！
Thank you!
ありがとー！嬉しい。
Thank you! I'm so happy.
私こそ嬉しいよ。
I'm the one who's happy.
いや、もうね、活動し始めてから、そらちゃんとは本当に一番こう...
Well, since I started my activities, Sora-chan and I have really had the most...
...AZKiと活動形態が近かったこともあって、
...similar style of activities to AZKi,
本当になんだろう、苦しい時も楽しい時も、なんか、
and really, through both hard times and fun times,
相談したりとか、色々連絡取ったりとかしていて、
we've consulted each other and kept in touch,
そう、だから本当になんか戦友でもあり、親友でもあり、
so she's truly like a comrade-in-arms and a best friend,
いや、本当になんか、やっぱりね、なんか色々思い出しちゃった、なんか。
and really... it brings back so many memories.
Our Bright Parade歌いながら。
While singing "Our Bright Parade".
色々あったもんね。
So much has happened, hasn't it?
そう、で、やっぱ活動始めた頃から仲良くしてもらっていました。
Yes, and we've been close since I first started out.
だから今もこうやって一緒に歌えることに、とってもとっても感謝しております。
So I'm very, very grateful to be able to sing with her like this even now.
いや、こちらこそ！今日一緒に歌えて本当に嬉しい、ありがとうね！
No, me too! I'm so happy we could sing together today, thank you!
ありがとー。あのね、本当にAZKi辛い時とか、こう挫けそうな時、
Thank you. You know, when things were really hard for me and I felt like giving up,
そらちゃんが前にいると思って、なんかその、そらちゃんの、
I would think of Sora-chan being ahead of me, and...
さ、いつもAZKiの前にはそらちゃんがいて、本当そのそらちゃんが頑張ってる姿とか、なんかこう、
Sora-chan was always there in front of me, and seeing her working so hard and...
いろんな活動してるの、その背中を見て、頑張ってこれました。
her various activities... looking at her back, I was able to keep going.
ありがとう。だから、本当今日は一緒に、このAZKiの誕生日にね、来てくれて歌ってくれて、本当にありがとうございました。
Thank you. So, really, thank you so much for coming and singing on my birthday today.
いやいや、私もいつもAZKiちゃんと一緒に歩いてこれたから、ここまで頑張ってこれてると思うので、
No, no, I think I've also been able to work hard until now because I've always been able to walk with you, AZKi-chan.
本当に今日お祝いに来れて、とっても嬉しいです！
So I'm really happy I could come and celebrate today!
大好きだよー！
I love you!
大好きだよー。
I love you too.
はい。そんなSorAZなんですけれども。
Yes. So, that's SorAZ, but...
なんと！
Guess what!
本日！
Today!
最速で披露したくて、二人の曲を作ってきましたー！
Wanting to perform it as soon as possible, we've made a song for the two of us!
なんとー！なんとー！
No way! No way!
ということで、まあ今日はみんなにいち早く聴いてもらうんですけれども、リリースは計画中、ということで。
So, everyone will get to hear it first today, but the release is still in the planning stages.
計画中だってよ。
It's in the planning stages!
後日発表します。
We'll announce it at a later date.
はい、発表されるかもよ。
Yes, it might be announced!
いよっ！SorAZなんかあるかもよ！
Yeah! There might be something for SorAZ!
はい。というわけでみんなに聴いてもらっちゃいましょうか。
Yes. So, shall we let everyone hear it?
それでは聴いてください。
Please listen.
せーの！
One, two!
Scale the walls!
吸った向こう側の気配
The presence on the other side we've breathed in,
きっと目に映そう
let's surely reflect it in our eyes.
Scale the walls
作詞・作曲 渡辺 翔 編曲 奈須野新平
Lyrics & Composition: Sho Watanabe, Arrangement: Shinpei Nasuno
誤魔化さず言って 言葉積み重ねよう
Say it without deceiving, let's stack up our words.
高すぎる壁さえも 飛んでしまうから
Because even walls that are too high, we'll fly over them.
通り抜けたって なにも楽しくないって
Even if we pass through, it's not fun at all.
Never enough 君が教えてくれていたんだ
"Never enough", you were teaching me that.
Ah 夢を散々掛け合わせ
Ah, mixing dreams together countless times.
時に So so 間違って
Sometimes making mistakes, so-so.
それも Laugh laugh 気にせずに
Don't mind that either, laugh laugh.
何度でも挑もう
Let's challenge ourselves over and over.
だって I know myself
Because I know myself.
意味のない評価で 世界比べないで
Don't compare worlds with meaningless evaluations.
叶えたい本音は 全てを包み込む太陽
The true feelings I want to fulfill are a sun that envelops everything.
いっそ好き放題 上を目指して
Rather, aiming for the top as we please,
立ちふさがる壁を登って
climbing the walls that stand in our way.
刻んでいきたいな
I want to carve it in.
そして次に望む 超えたいあの未来
And then, the next thing I wish for, that future I want to surpass.
想像したら
When I imagined it,
鼓動が聞こえたんだ
I heard my heart beating.
作り込んだ道なんて
Paths we have made,
全部従わず行こう
let's go without following them at all.
響く音のまま
Following the echoing sound,
心が赴くまま
wherever my heart leads.
ずっと君なら君なら
With you, always with you,
一緒になんでも築ける
we can build anything together.
躓いて視界が何も見えなくなっても
Even if I stumble and my vision becomes unclear,
振り向いて笑えるそんな場所がある
there's a place where I can look back and smile.
ただ楽しもう
Let's just have fun.
夢を散々掛け合わせ
Mix our dreams together thoroughly,
時にそうそう間違って
sometimes making mistakes along the way.
それも Laugh laugh 気にせずに
But Laugh laugh, without a care about that,
何度でも挑もう
let's challenge it over and over.
いつも Be yourself
Always be yourself.
試さないとほら何も始まらない
Look, nothing starts unless you try.
些細な勇気で明日を変えるまでもっと
Until a little courage changes tomorrow, even more.
意味のない評価で世界比べないで
Don't compare the world with meaningless evaluations.
叶えたい本音はすべてを包み込む太陽
The true feelings I want to fulfill are a sun that envelops everything.
いっそ好き放題上を目指して
I'd rather aim for the top as I please,
立ちはだかる壁を登って
and climb the walls that stand in my way.
刻んでいきたいな
I want to engrave it.
そして次に臨む越えたいあの未来
And then, look towards the next future I want to surpass.
抱こう壮大な未来
Let's embrace a grand future.
そらちゃん今日はありがとう！
Sora-chan, thank you for today!
ありがとう！AZKiちゃん、おめでとう！
Thank you! Congratulations, AZKi-chan!
ここまでの1,690日。
1,690 days up to this point.
初めの頃の私が歩いていた道は、
The path I walked in the beginning
いつも道標があって、
always had a signpost,
分からないところでもちゃんと歩けてた。
and I could walk properly even in places I didn't know.
雨の日も、風の日も、寒い日も、暑い日も、
On rainy days, windy days, cold days, and hot days,
最初の地図に描かれた通りに歩いた。
I walked according to what was drawn on the first map.
2枚目に渡された地図。
The second map I was given...
真っ白だった。
It was completely blank.
いつも矢印の方向に進んでたから、
Because I had always followed the arrows,
何も分からなくなった。
I became lost.
頭も真っ白になったし、初めて「孤独」や「不安」を覚えた。
My mind went blank too, and I felt 'loneliness' and 'anxiety' for the first time.
世界が怖かった。
I was afraid of the world.
それでも私なりに考えて、考えて考えて、
Even so, I thought in my own way, I thought and thought,
初めて地図を作ることにした。
and decided to make a map for the first time.
きっとスローペースだったけど、
It was surely at a slow pace,
描いているうちに何だか景色が色々見える様になった。
but as I drew, I started to see various landscapes.
最初の地図に描かれていたゴールも飛び越えて、
Surpassing the goal drawn on the first map,
今では道標なしでどこでもすぐに辿り着ける様になった。
I can now reach anywhere instantly without a signpost.
成長だ。
That's growth.
そして今日、私は3枚目の地図へと進む。
And today, I move on to the third map.
たくさんやりたい事だらけで、まだまだ手探りだけど、
I'm full of things I want to do, and I'm still feeling my way, but
今の私は一人じゃない。
now I'm not alone.
たくさんの開拓者のみんなが、ずっとそばにいてくれたことを、
I feel strongly once again that all of you Pioneers
改めて強く感じてる。
have been by my side all along.
新たな決意を持って、
With a new determination,
これからもみんなと一緒に、私は歌い続ける。
I will continue to sing with everyone from now on.
エンドロールは終わらない
The Endroll Never Ends
扉の向こう繋いで 生まれたはずの世界は
The world that should have been born by connecting beyond the door,
思うよりずっと難しくて 夢が零れた
was much more difficult than I thought, and my dreams spilled over.
...てた
...faded.
伝えたいことなんて　いくつもありはしないから
Because there aren't many things I want to tell you.
儚く脆い僕の声は　掠れて揺れてた
My fleeting and fragile voice was raspy and wavering.
よし
Alright.
三度目の何とだって　続ける意味を探して
Searching for a reason to continue for the third time.
未開拓だった道の先
Ahead on the unexplored path,
これでいいと　よかったとそう言えるまで
until I can say it's fine and it was for the best.
このまま終われば誰かの美談として消費されていくでしょうか？
If it ends like this, will it just be consumed as a fine story?
ずっと後悔ばかり思い出す日々を　背負って笑う　今だ
Now is the time to laugh, carrying days filled with regrets.
そんな悲しい顔をしないできっと　間違ってないから
Don't look so sad, because I'm surely not wrong.
間違いになんて絶対にしないよ
I will never let it be a mistake.
しないよ
I won't.
すれ違いのひとつふたつだって　気にしないように過ごしてた
I spent my time trying not to care about a few misunderstandings.
青さの宿ったこの身体を愛してたから
Because I loved this body dwelling in youth.
何者にもなれなくて　もがき続けた時間ごと
Along with all the time spent struggling to be someone.
肯定できるかわからない　わからないけど
I don't know if I can affirm it, I just don't know.
辛ければ辛いほど　笑い話にもなるでしょう？
The harder it is, the better it makes for a funny story, right?
君の声だって聞こえるから　大丈夫だよ、大丈夫だよ！
Because I can hear your voice too, it's okay, it's okay!
最高な日も　最悪な日も　音楽と共に刻んできた
Both the best and worst days, I've etched them with music.
これが生き様だと呼べるならば　目的地なんて無い
If this can be called a way of life, then there is no destination.
僕は生きている
I am alive.
ごめん
I'm sorry.
何度願い　何度痛み　何度怒り　何度嘘をついてしまったんだ
How many wishes, pains, angers, and lies have I told?
こんなみすぼらしくて恥ずかしくて真面目過ぎる僕を　隠さずに晒すよ
I'll expose my shabby, shameful, overly serious self without hiding.
ずっと誰にも言えないこの気持ちを　吐き出してしまいたい
I want to spit out these feelings that I could never tell anyone.
君を傷つけてしまうよ
I'll end up hurting you.
初めて夢を描いた時からもう何年経った？
How many years have passed since I first dreamed?
気付いたらみんな居なくなっていた
Before I knew it, everyone was gone.
僕らは出会いと別れを繰り返していく
We keep repeating meetings and partings.
ただ時間が過ぎて終わりが来る
Time just passes and the end comes.
「これでいい？」「後悔は？」あとは自分で決めるだけだ
“Is this okay?” “Any regrets?” All that's left is for me to decide.
綺麗で歪な思い出を歌にしよう
Let's turn these beautiful, warped memories into a song.
何回でも　そう何回でも　届けよう
Over and over, yes, over and over, let's deliver it.
残酷な夢の世界で　誰かの歌が聞こえる
In a cruel dream world, I hear someone's song.
今日も音楽に救われて僕は生きている
Saved by music again today, I am alive.
ということで、お届けしたのは
AZKiの新曲「エンドロールは終わらない」でした。
And so, that was AZKi's new song,
"The Credits Never End."
えーこちらの曲は、我らが瀬名航さんに
書き下ろしていただきました。
This song was specially written for me
by the wonderful Wataru Sena.
えー今までのAZKiの思いだったり、そして
新しい一歩を踏み出すための楽曲となっています。
It's a song that carries AZKi's feelings up until now
and marks a new step forward.
どうでしたか？はい。
How was it? I hope you liked it.
えーこの曲には裏話があるので、
また今度お話ししますね。はい。
There's a back story to this song,
so I'll share it with you another time.
ということで、皆さんお待たせいたしました。
Alright then, sorry to keep you waiting everyone.
ここで重大発表させてください。
Please let me make a major announcement here.
ということで、重大発表の映像がございます。
ご覧ください！
We have a video for the major announcement.
Please take a look!
重大発表
MAJOR ANNOUNCEMENT
「エンドロールは終わらない」
7月1日24時より先行配信スタート
"The Credits Never End"
Pre-release starts on July 1st at 24:00
2023.10.4 AZKi メジャーデビュー決定
2023.10.4 AZKi Major Debut Decided
2023.10.4 メジャーデビューEPリリース
2023.10.4 Major Debut EP Release
AZKi、10月4日にビクターエンタテインメントより
メジャーデビューが決定いたしました！
AZKi's major debut under Victor Entertainment
has been decided for October 4th!
はい、ということで、重大発表はこちらのメジャーデビュー、
そしてEPのリリースを10月4日にさせていただくことになりました。
Yes, so the major announcement is my major debut
and the EP release on October 4th.
本日8時から予約開始いたします。
Pre-orders will start from 8:00 PM today.
そして、本日24時に先ほど歌った
「エンドロールは終わらない」が配信開始！
And at midnight tonight, the song I just performed,
"The Credits Never End," will be released!
お願いします。えー詳細は、ツイート、などをチェックして、ください！
Please do. For details, please check the tweets and other sources!
はい。
Yes.
ということで、今日こういう発表をすることが、できたのは、
So, being able to make this announcement today is...
本当に、本当に、今日ここまで応援して、くださった皆さんがいたからだと思っています。
...truly, truly thanks to everyone who has supported me until now.
えー、ルートα、えー、βを飛び越えて、えー、ルートγの世界に、やってきました。
I've jumped over Route Alpha and Beta and arrived in the world of Route Gamma.
この、ルートが開けたのは、応援してくれる、開拓者の皆が、いたからです。
This route opened up because of all the Pioneers supporting me.
えー、アーティストとして、音楽の活動も、精一杯、頑張って、いくので、これからも、どうぞ、よろしくお願いします。
As an artist, I'll continue to give my all in my music activities, so I look forward to your continued support.
えー詳しく、は、AZKiメジャーデビュー特設サイトを、ご覧、ください。
For more details, please visit the AZKi major debut special website.
そして、最後に、誕生日といえば、まだ、あれが、あれを、発表していませんでしたね。
And finally, speaking of birthdays, I haven't announced *that* yet.
ということで、こちら！
So, here it is!
AZKi生誕グッズ2023！
AZKi Birthday Goods 2023!
ということで、このあと、こちらも、20時に、発売開始になります。
These will also go on sale starting today at 8 PM.
ということで、駆け足になりますが、1つずつ紹介していきたいと思います。まずは、こちら。
It'll be quick, but I'd like to introduce them one by one. First, this.
はい。B2タペストリー。
Yes, the B2 Tapestry.
えー一緒にね、今回のテーマは、一緒に旅をするということで、旅をしているところを、描き下ろして、いただきました。
The theme this time is "traveling together," so I had this illustration made of us traveling together.
イラストレーターは、松うに先生。
The illustrator is Matsuuni-sensei.
えー今回、発売するグッズね、こちらの、あの、キービジュアルなんですけれども、よく見といてください。はい。
This is the key visual for the goods being released this time, so take a good look. Yes.
ということで、あの、この身につけているグッズも、これから、紹介します。次は、こちら。
I'll also be introducing the items shown in the illustration. Next is this.
SNS風アクリルキーホルダー、ということで、旅行先で、一緒に、AZKiと、写真が撮れる、グッズに、なっております。
The SNS-style Acrylic Key Holder. It's an item that lets you take photos together with AZKi while traveling.
いろんな場所で、一緒に写真を撮ってください。えーイラストは、すずみしろ先生の、描き下ろしになっております。
Please take photos together in various places. The illustration is by Suzumishiro-sensei.
そして、こちら。
And next is this.
ミニドラムバッグ、ということで、キービジュアルのAZKiと、お揃いの、ミニドラムバッグです。
The Mini Drum Bag. It's the same mini drum bag AZKi has in the key visual.
ミニだけど、結構、容量があるので、使い勝手、よしです。
It's "mini," but it has a lot of capacity, so it's very useful.
続きまして、こちら。
Moving on, this.
キャップ。こちらも、キービジュアルのAZKiが、身につけている、お揃いのキャップに、なっています。
The Cap. This is also a matching cap that AZKi is wearing in the key visual.
シンプルで、とっても、ロゴも、可愛いでしょ？普段使いも、できるデザインに、なっております。
It's simple, and the logo is cute, right? It's a design you can use every day.
えーミニドラムバッグと、えね、ロゴが一緒なので、この、これを、これを被って、
The logo is the same as the mini drum bag, so if you put this on...
そして、ミニドラムバッグを、背負って、えー旅に、出よう、ということで、そんなテーマの、グッズになっております。
...and carry the bag, you can go on a journey. That's the theme of these goods.
さらに、こちら。
Furthermore, this.
記念ボイス、えー「きみとあてのない旅」、ということで、旅をテーマにした、シチュエーションボイスに、なって、おります。
The Commemorative Voice, "A Journey with You with No Destination." It's a situation voice with a travel theme.
そして、最後に、こちら。
And finally, this.
えー誕生日記念フルセット。今、紹介した、グッズ4種類と、ボイス1種、
The Birthday Celebration Full Set. It includes the 4 types of goods and 1 voice I just introduced...
そして、特典で、ポストカードと、ボイスが、付いてきちゃいます。
...plus a bonus postcard and another voice.
えー前回、数量限定で、買えなかった、人も、いた、みたいなので、今回は、全員に、
It seems some people couldn't buy it last time because it was limited, so this time...
なんと、フルセット買って、いただくと、直筆サインを、付けます。付けます。はい。
...everyone who buys the full set will get a handwritten signature. I'll include it. Yes.
えーっと、最近ね、AZKiを知ってくれた、そこの、開拓者の、君。はい。
To the Pioneers who have recently come to know AZKi...
AZKiが真心を込めて、サインを書きますので、ぜひぜひ、フルセット手に、入れて、ください。
I'll put my heart and soul into signing these, so please do get the full set.
はい。ということで、めちゃくちゃ、駆け足になりましたが、本日は、AZKi生誕ライブ2023に、お越し、いただき、ありがとう、ございました。
Yes. So, it was quite a rush, but thank you all for coming to AZKi Birthday Live 2023 today.
えー、本当に、今、ここに、AZKiが、いることは、奇跡、なんですね。本当に、奇跡みたいな、ことです。
Truly, the fact that AZKi is here right now is a miracle. It's really like a miracle.
この瞬間を、えー見守ってくれて、本当に、ありがとう、ございました。
Thank you so much for watching over this moment.
これからも、一緒に、世界を、作って、いこうね。
Let's continue to create the world together.
えー私の、目的地は、いつだって、君と一緒に、たどり着いた、場所です。
My destination is always the place I reach together with you.
ということで、AZKiでした。みんな、ありがとう。また、会いましょう。
So, that's all from AZKi. Thank you, everyone. Let's meet again.
なんと、このあと、20時15分から、アンコールライブが、ありますので、メンバーシップ、開拓者組合の皆さんは、すぐに、お会いしましょう。
And, there will be an encore live starting from 8:15 PM, so members of the Pioneers' Association, let's meet again soon.
ということで、AZKiでした。ありがとうございましたー。
So, that's all from AZKi. Thank you very much!
いつも、道に迷ったときには、君がくれた声のことを思い出していました。
Whenever I got lost, I would remember the voice you gave me.
今日、5回目の誕生日を迎えることができたのは、君がいたから。本当に、ありがとう。
I was able to celebrate my 5th birthday today because you were there. Thank you so much.
これからも、一緒に歩いていこうね。大好きだよ。
Let's keep walking together. I love you.
AZKi 2023.07.01
いつも道に迷ったときに
Whenever I lost my way,
隣にいてくれたこと、思い出していたら、
thinking back on how you were always by my side,
今日 5回目の誕生日を迎えることが
I realized that the reason I'm able to
できたことに気づいたから、
celebrate my 5th birthday today is because of you,
本当にありがとう。
so thank you so much.
これからも一緒に歩いていこうね。
Let's keep walking forward together.
大好きだよ。
I love you.